<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: meta programming | Brian Mehrman]]></title>
  <link href="http://brianmehrman.github.io/blog/categories/meta-programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brianmehrman.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-03-31T19:53:15-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://brianmehrman.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brian Mehrman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[class_eval vs define_method]]></title>
    <link href="http://brianmehrman.github.io/blog/2017/04/26/class-eval-vs-define-method/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-26T17:10:42-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brianmehrman.github.io/blog/2017/04/26/class-eval-vs-define-method</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>Meta Programming</h1>

<p>Having to write redundant methods can lead to hundreds of lines of code that can
be hard to maintain. Meta programming provides us with tools that allow us to write
code that writes its self.</p>

<!--more-->


<h1>Class Eval</h1>

<p>class_eval opens the class and adds the method to the class itself. While this takes
longer to define a method it puts the new method in the ancestor chain where it can
be accessed quicker than if you used define_method.</p>

<pre><code>class Test; end

Test.class_eval("def new_method() 1+1 end")

t = Test.new
t.new_method # =&gt; 2
</code></pre>

<h1>Define Method</h1>

<p>define_method will define an instance method on the receiver using the block or
Proc provided. While faster to create the method it has a little overhead that will
slow the methods execution down. While this performance hit is relatively small it
has an accumulative effect that can slow down code if the method is called
multiple times in a row.</p>

<pre><code>class Test; end

Test.define_method(:new_method) do
  1 + 1
end

# or using a proc

a_proc = Proc.new { 1 + 1 }
Test.define_method(:another_method, a_proc)

t = Test.new
t.new_method # =&gt; 2
t.another_method # =&gt; 2
</code></pre>

<h1>Instruction Sequence</h1>

<p>When Ruby compiles the code it will create instructions that YARV. These instructions
will differ between different that different ways you can define a method even if
the code in that method are basically the same.</p>

<pre><code># Defines the methods normally
module Foo
  def my_method
    'module method'
  end
end

# Defines the method using class eval
module ClassFoo
  class_eval &lt;&lt;-RUBY
    def my_method
      'Class evaluated method'
    end
  RUBY
end

# Defines the methods using define_method
module DefineFoo
  define_method 'my_method' do
    'Define method method'
  end
end

# Base Class
class MyClass
  def my_method
    'class method'
  end
end

# Subclass normal methods
class MySubclass &lt; MyClass
  include Foo
end

# class using class eval methods
class CEClass &lt; MyClass
  include ClassFoo
end

# Class using define method methods
class DMClass &lt; MyClass
  include DefineFoo
end

class_evaluated = CEClass.new
dynamiclly_defined = DMClass.new
normally_defined = MySubclass.new
</code></pre>

<p>Above we have three modules that each implement the same method in different ways; def, class_eval, and define_method. Each module has been included in its own class.</p>

<p>With the help of RubyVM&rsquo;s RubyVM::InstructionSequence we can get a human readable string of instruction sequences for a specific method. Using the disassemble method we will see each instruction.</p>

<h1>Using def</h1>

<pre><code>irb(main):023:0&gt; puts RubyVM::InstructionSequence.disasm(normally_defined.method(:my_method))
== disasm: &lt;rubyvm::instructionsequence:my_method&gt;
0000 trace            8                                               (  20)
0002 trace            1                                               (  21)
0004 putstring        "module method"
0006 trace            16                                              (  22)
0008 leave                                                            (  21)
&lt;/rubyvm::instructionsequence:my_method&gt;
Using class_eval
irb(main):019:0&gt; puts RubyVM::InstructionSequence.disasm(class_evaluated.method(:my_method))
== disasm: &lt;rubyvm::instructionsequence:my_method&gt;===============
0000 trace            8                                               (   1)
0002 trace            1                                               (   2)
0004 putstring        "Class evaluated method"
0006 trace            16                                              (   3)
0008 leave                                                            (   2)
&lt;/rubyvm::instructionsequence:my_method&gt;
Using define_method
irb(main):020:0&gt; puts RubyVM::InstructionSequence.disasm(dynamiclly_evaluated.method(:my_method))
== disasm: &lt;rubyvm::instructionsequence:block in=""&gt;&lt;module:definefoo&gt;@/Users/brian.mehrman/ruby_projects/lightning_talks/class_eval-vs-define_method/dynamic_methods.rb&gt;
== catch table
| catch type: redo   st: 0002 ed: 0006 sp: 0000 cont: 0002
| catch type: next   st: 0002 ed: 0006 sp: 0000 cont: 0006
|------------------------------------------------------------------------
0000 trace            256                                             (  13)
0002 trace            1                                               (  14)
0004 putstring        "Define method method"
0006 trace            512                                             (  15)
0008 leave                                                            (  14)
&lt;/module:definefoo&gt;&lt;/rubyvm::instructionsequence:block&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>At a quick glance we can see a major difference between the instructions for the method created using define_method. This extra step helps to slow down the methods execution. What is this extra step from, one word &lsquo;closures&rsquo;.</p>

<h1>Closures</h1>

<p>Blocks, Procs, and Lambdas are types of closures that are used everyday. A closure simply put is a self contained section of code that can be passed around that you can execute at a later point in your code.</p>

<pre><code>arr = [1,2,3]


# Block
def log(&amp;block)
  block.call
end

log do
  puts arr.first
end

# Proc
log = Proc.new { |arg| puts arg }
log.call(arr.first)

# Lambdas
log = lambda { |arg| puts arg }
log.call(arr.first)
</code></pre>

<p>These closures can be great to store code that you need to execute later, however executing that code later comes at a performance cost.</p>

<p>In the case of define_method, the block passed to define_method is stored for use later by instance_eval. It is not clear exactly when the instance_eval occurs, whether it is when the method is defined or when it is executed is not entirely clear.</p>

<p>The class_eval instantiates a new parser and compiles the source. Each method definition in the class_eval version does not share instruction sequences, where the define_method version does.</p>

<h1>Conclusion</h1>

<p>While define_method is quick to create your method it is slower to execute. It also is placed higher up the ancestor chain, slowing the method lookup as well. Define method is great when you need to create a method that will be used in low volume. Using class_eval is slower to define the method, yet it provides the benefit of executing faster than if it were defined using define_method. The methods defined using class_eval also are placed lower in the ancestor chain.</p>

<p>Meta-programming is a great way to dry up your code and create code that can essentially write itself. This benefit comes at a cost, either at compile time or at run time. Knowing what that cost is can help in deciding what approach you show take.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
